Yuexin Mao

DATA ANALYST/SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN - FINSTATS.COM

Vernon, CT

yuexin.mao@engr.uconn.edu - (203) 392-4798

Ph.D candidate in Computer Science and Engineering with hands-on experience, developing and implementing machine learning algorithms to facilitate stock/trade positioning strategies, along with extensive university research analyzing Twitter volume spikes and their relationship to identifying return-on-investment opportunities for stock transactions. Exploring career opportunities as a Data Scientist in the financial services or information technology field.

WORK EXPERIENCE

DATA ANALYST/SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN

FINSTATS.COM - Storrs, CT - June 2013 to Present

Stock Tweet Burst Detection and Trading Recommendation System

- Developed and implemented a tweet bursts detection trading system that provides real-time trading signals (Python, R and MySQL). The system integrates a scheme to collect real-time tweets mentioning S&P 500 stocks and detect tweet bursts, a filter for analyzing users who post tweets and content to evaluate tweet bursts, a classification model to evaluate trading probability and recommendations on specific stocks for trading.
- Developed a trading tracking algorithm to monitor stock positions and recommend optimal trade entry and exit time.
- Put Option Selling Recommendation System
- Developed and implemented an online put option selling system (Python, R and MySQL). The system uses Twitter volume spikes and stock option trading probability as the basis for formulating recommendations on put option with a specific strike price for a particular stock to sell.
- Developed a mechanism to generate a daily put selling report including stock charts with automated web server upload.
- Tracked performance for all 467 advised put option trades from January 2013, achieving a 112.96% annual rate-of-return, with 95.08% trades generating positive profit.

Resumé)

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT - Storrs, CT - January 2010 to Present

Using Twitter Volume Spikes to Assist Stock Options Trading

- Investigate the assumption of the Black-Scholes model when stocks have Twitter volume spikes.
- Proposed and implemented a spread selling strategy for stock option trading. Demonstrated that even in a competitive setting, using one year stock market data, this strategy achieved a 34.3% gain, while S&P 500 increased by 12.8%.
- Analyze Twitter Volume Spikes and Using Twitter Volume Spikes to Assist Stock Trading
- Implemented a Twitter tweets collection and analysis scheme using Python and MySQL to collect tweets that mention S&P 500 stocks and identify Twitter volume spikes.
- Analyzed timing of Twitter volume spikes and whether they were expected. Investigated possible causes for the spikes.
- Developed a Bayesian classifier that uses Twitter volume spikes to facilitate stock trading with a simulation showing an 8.6% gain over 1 month and 15.0% gain over 3 months.

- Correlating S&P 500 stocks with Twitter data
- Investigated the correlation between S&P 500 stock indicators and Twitter data; showed strong correlation between the number of tweets mentioning stocks to stock trading volume.
- Developed a multinomial logistic regression model to predict stock trading volume in classes on each trading day. This model achieved 57.3% precision for predicting low trading volume and 67.2% precision for predicting high volume over 6 months.
- ♦ Iterative LT Decoding Algorithm for Binary and Non-binary Galois Field
- Designed and implemented a new iterative LT decoding algorithm for Binary field using Matlab and C++.
- Improved the original LT decoding algorithm for Non-binary field.
- Policy Research and Mixed Methods: A Technique for Compensation for Attrition Bias
- Developed a network analysis method to compensate the attrition bias using Matlab.
- · Evaluated and compensated the Commission social network using compensation method.

RESEARCH ANALYST/INTERN

GENERAL ELECTRIC EDGE LAB - Stamford, CT - January 2011 to May 2011

Developed a mobile payment system prototype (JAVA) on Android OS for GE.

- Conducted research on NFC (Near Field Communication) technologies to be used in mobile payment systems.
- Member of team advised by GE Director and Project Manager, as well as two UConn professors.
- Provided final delivery of NFC implementation plan to GE; project partially completed due to lab shutdown.

SOFTWARE ENGINEER/WEB APPLICATIONS DEVELOPER

INDEPENDENT SOFTWARE - New Haven, CT - August 2009 to May 2010

Developed web applications using PHP, JavaScript and HTML, combined with MySQL.

Implemented and managed an open source project management software for the company.

RESEARCH ENGINEERING EXPERIENCE

EDUCATION

Master of Science in ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING

UNIVERSITY OF BRIDGEPORT - Bridgeport, CT May 2009

Bachelor of Electrical Engineering and Bachelor of English

UNIVERSITY OF ELECTRICAL SCIENCE & TECHNOLOGY OF CHINA May 2007

Ph.D in COMPUTER SCIENCE & ENGINEERING

UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT - Storrs, CT

LINKS

http://www.finstats.com/sp500.htm

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

COMPETENCIES

• Mathematics & Statistics Knowledge • Machine Learning (Proficient in R, Matlab)

- Programming Skills (Proficient in Python, familiar with Java, C and C++)
- Database Development & Management (Proficient in MySQL and PostegreSQL)
- Data Analytics & Visualization Social Media Data Collection/Analysis
- Stock Market/Option Data Analysis Stock Trading Strategies

SKILLS and TOOLS

Python; C/C++; Java; R Programming; Matlab; PHP; JavaScript; HTML; Minitab; MySQL; PostegreSQL; MS SQL; Hadoop; Tableau; SVN; GIT; Vi/Vim; Visual Studio; Netbeans; Eclipse; Linux; Unix OS; Mac OS; Windows OS.